Software Engineering Radio episode 20,
interview with Michael Stahl.
Welcome
Michael to Software Engineering Radio.
Why don't you introduce yourself and
explain to the listeners what you do in
real life?
Sure. Hello Marcus. Nice to hear you. So
basically my background is I'm started
1991 basically at Siemens Corporate
Technology.
And I worked at the beginning in the
area of software architecture and object
orientation. So these were the main
focus
on the software corporate technology
department of Siemens. I then became
member of the OMG.
So that was the first start for me to
deal more and uh
think more about middleware. And I also
started
almost the same time to work on patterns
with Frank Buschmann. So
then I started to switch from the
software architecture department to the
department which was dealing with
distributed and parallel systems.
And became head of the distributed
systems team. And in the same time Frank
and me were cooperating on the first
book on pattern-oriented software
architecture.
Rather famous POSA
book.
Yes, absolutely. And then we also after
Frank joined my new department which
then became the software architecture
department again, we worked on the POSA
2 book. And I'm currently lead of a team
focusing on distributed systems,
middleware, software architecture. So
that's basically my research focus and
I'm also currently coordinating research
program at Siemens which is dealing with
software product lines and platforms for
distributed systems. So basically
middleware and software architecture and
patterns have been my main central
research working areas at Siemens.
You you say research. Are you like
are you heading a department? Are you a
researcher or
are you a Siemens internal consultant?
So what's your what's your work schedule
like?
So I have basically two hats on. My
first hat is I'm lead of a team of 12
people who are working in research
projects but mainly in customer
projects. So where we are doing some
architecture consulting, architecture
reviews, uh
helping customers to get the systems
right, also help helping them to develop
the systems basically. But we also have
another 1/3 of our time spending for
let's say research things like
model-driven software development,
aspect orientation, service orientation,
all of the things which are relevant for
Siemens.
Actually these will be interesting
topics to talk about later. A&M
model-driven and service-oriented
architecture and stuff. So I didn't know
that you that you were on the OMG. What
what did you do there?
I was member of the OMG on behalf of
Siemens. So basically I was more but I
must must make sure I'm well I was more
observing things and not so
standardizing or
defining things. So basically Siemens
was interested in observing what will
happen there. So that was the time when
CORBA came in the in the focus of the of
the community. So that's basically was
my main interest in the Object
Management Group that time.
Okay.
Okay. So maybe let's let's start talking
about middleware a little bit.
Most people probably know what
middleware is more more less but do you
want to give us some kind of a
definition or or what's the typical
cases where middleware is used? We
already had this this episode in
remoting patterns where we talked a bit
about middleware, but we didn't provide
a general definition and we didn't
outline the various kinds of middleware,
so maybe that's something you could do
now.
Sure.
So, what is middleware? The problem with
this question is that there are probably
only wrong answers, but I will try.
Most important thing or the most naive
answer is basically that middleware is
anything between the operating system
and the application layer and that's
basically where the name comes from.
Middleware means sitting in the middle
between the application and the
operating system. And basically
middleware is providing from my
viewpoint is platform
that is providing services to the
applications in a system agnostic way.
The problem with this definition, of
course, is that this is almost true for
everything like directory services,
databases and
libraries.
Everything. Libraries, yes, you're
right. Dynamic link libraries, all kinds
of libraries. So, basically most experts
that I know think that middleware is
mainly communication middleware. So,
basically it's something which helps you
to communicate among different
applications. So, it's basically a kind
of transparency layer
maybe consisting of let's say a stack of
adapters that are mediating between
system infrastructure and applications
in order to allow applications to
communicate with each other.
Uh
The problem is that most people think
that
CORBA, COM,
Windows Communication Framework or Java
RMI, that's basically middleware and
that's the only possible middleware
solutions and they really think or I I
have met many people who really think
that remoting middleware is everything
about middleware, but that's not true.
So, it's more than remoting.
So, so um
other paradigms are like messaging and
these kinds of things, but that's also a
communication middleware. Would you say
that things like component containers
such as J2EE EJBs or or COM+? Would you,
uh, also call this middleware or is this
like transaction middleware or component
middleware or communication middleware?
Do you distinguish between those?
I distinguish between different things.
From my viewpoint, there's remoting
middleware which is the basic layer in
order to communicate using a kind of
invocation-based paradigm. Then I see
something like messaging middleware, MQ
Series, MSMQ and so on.
Then eventing middleware, transaction
monitors, for instance, are different
kinds of middleware solutions. And even
service orientation, for for instance,
is also kind of middleware. It's, maybe
a special case of messaging, but it's
also a special kind of meta middleware
in order to interoperate between the
different other middlewares. Grid
Grid computing. So, basically, a lot of
different kinds of middleware systems,
but I think the mainstream systems are
basically
messaging and remoting.
If if people have to decide which, uh,
which which communication paradigm to
use, do you have any any like best
practices there? When do I I mean, it's
typically clear if I need a component
middleware or transaction monitor, then
then I have to use, I don't know, EJB or
COM+, but how do I decide whether to use
things like CORBA or, uh, messaging
middleware on the other side?
I think one of the most important issues
here is, if you have something like
long-term transactions or things where
you don't need an immediate answer, for
instance, or things where you have, uh,
where you're more focusing on data and
not on services which are executed on a
remote node are more or better suitable
in order to use messaging middleware.
There are even some things which you
cannot definitely do with remoting
middleware. For instance, if you think
about I'm sending you a request and I
need multiple replies. For instance, I'm
getting multiple fragments of the same
video stream. So, that's basically
something which you can definitely not
do with remoting middleware.
Right, but that's
that would be streaming and not and not
messaging either. So, that's maybe a
third kind of middleware.
Yeah, absolutely. So, audio video
streaming is basically a complete other
kind of mis- middleware and I don't see
any
big standards out there in the community
which we can use here at the moment at
least.
Mhm. Um some people say that messaging
is better because it decouples systems.
Um and I always think that's I mean,
technically it's true. So, if I send a
message and the other side isn't
available, then the message can be
buffered and, you know, you can dispatch
it later and I get the reply later. But,
in many systems that, you know, if I
need the reply that then that's
technically decoupled, but the process
that I want to run needs the reply, so
that doesn't really help me. So, so can
you give us two or three examples where
messaging middleware is really like
the solution and and remoting doesn't
work?
Sure. For instance, consider you have a
network management systems consisting of
multiple devices and you want to send
around
let's say error notifications or other
things from all of these different
devices to manage by the network
management systems. So, basically I
think that's something where you can't
really work with remoting middleware
because if you would use remoting
middleware, that would mean that if you
have something like an agent, you would
have to
notify everyone about every event which
is appearing in your system. So, bas-
basically
example for this was Microsoft tried in
COM+ to have something like
tight coupled events. So, basically that
meant if you want to send an event to
let's say 100 subscribers, they
definitely used a remoting middleware
approach. So, they had to send
each message to each of the subscribers,
which does not work. So, that's a basic
example where you have some
lot of subscribers, lot of
recipients of your messages. Another
example is, for instance, if you send
something like a purchase order to a
order system or something like this,
which is
which may be take a long time to be
processed, for instance, uh like 1 hour.
Then you would not try to make this a
remoting approach because then you would
have to deal with blocking
synchronicity and asynchronicity and all
of these things which make your life
really very complicated if you are using
remoting middleware for for that kind of
purpose.
When we talk about middleware, I think
we obviously have to talk about web
services, too. So, um
most people have a very distinct opinion
with regards to web services. Like many
people like it and say, like, that's the
solution for all of our problems. Other
people hate it because they say it's the
same stuff as always, just with all
those XML angle brackets. So, so what's
your opinion on web services? Were were
uh did you use them? Are they used at
Siemens?
Yes, sure. Um we basically made a little
conference at Siemens last year where we
looked at what people are doing at
Siemens with all of these
service-oriented architecture stuff.
And basically I got two opinions on
that. My first opinion is if you only
look at web services, then this might be
something which is interesting for
integrating different kinds of systems
on an enterprise level. And it won't
work for things like uh building
real-time or embedded systems. So,
basically it's for me it's a kind of
meta middleware.
And I think the primary value of web
services is the paradigm which is behind
web services, which I call
service-oriented architectures. So, for
my viewpoint, SOA is not something which
is a one-to-one relationship with web
services. It's more something like a
paradigm, which can be also used with
other technologies like messaging
middleware, for instance.
Right. Okay, so uh we'll talk about uh
service oriented architecture in a
minute. Um just want to go back to web
services very briefly. So,
there are two camps in the web services
uh world. One is basically this REST
thing, where people say, "Just use HTTP
get and and put and all that stuff with
as simple as possible XML schemas to to
transport data." And then there is the
standards movement, which, you know,
these WS
I X Y star, whatever.
Um do you see uh an adoption of all
those WS standards, or are people more
pragmatic in saying that, you know, we
just use HTTP and send over the network,
maybe using SOAP, but otherwise just a
little bit WSDL? What do you see? What's
What's the adoption rate of all those
WSI standards?
Uh
a little bit it reminds me of what
happened to CORBA. When you remember
CORBA, it started with a very small and
very simple communication uh broker.
Mhm.
And then
after a while, people recognized that
you need security services and other
services in order to make really big
enterprise based applications. And
exactly the same thing is now happening
with web services. It started very
simple. So, basically the SOAP
originally stood for simple object
access protocol. And you remember it
isn't simple, it's not object oriented,
and it's not uh based on access. So,
basically, it's just uh renamed SOAP
now. Basically,
I think that's really funny that people
redefine an abbreviation to not mean uh
the thing anymore for which it was
originally defined. So, just, you know,
remove the meaning of the term.
Absolutely. And if you look at all of
these standards, it was the same for
CORBA. You got a a thing a bunch 12 or
13 CORBA services. And if you look at
the real CORBA implementations, then
even now, 10 years later, you only will
see three or four different CORBA
services which are really delivered with
each of the CORBA products. And I think
the same thing will happen with web
services. I don't think that anyone is
really able to have 20 or 30 WS services
available with this web service tool
kits. And I think the worst thing about
it is that there are even conflicting
standards. People are not
unified in their opinion about all of
these different WS standards. There are
different standards for coordination and
for other things, for conversation. And
I'm really skeptical. So, basically, I
think you should really take it a
pragmatic, take what is available within
IBM, Microsoft, BA, whatever you're
using for it, and try to come up with a
solution that is really able to use all
of these things which are available. And
don't wait for having 30, 40, or
whatever number of web service standards
which you need. So, because that
basically will never happen.
So, so going back to CORBA, I think the
stand the services that have been
deployed were I think like notification,
transactions, security, and of course
naming and trading. So, maybe that's
maybe that's a sign what's going to
prevail in in the web services world.
And
and it's really interesting because as
soon as web started as the web service
paradigm and evolution started, everyone
told me that SOAP and SOA and web
services would be very simple, very
usable. And now it really
is has the same kind of complexity or is
starting to have the same kind of
complexity as all of the other CORBA and
DCOM and other middleware solutions.
Actually, I like your your calling
web services a kind of meta middleware,
a middleware to integrate various system
partitions which use other middlewares
internally. From my point of view,
that's also the most sensible use of
using web services because usually there
the overhead that you get from all those
XML stuff doesn't really matter.
Absolutely.
So, so let's talk about SOA, um
same old architecture as some people
say.
Or what what's the the other thing was
uh stupid overhyped acronym. But of
course it stands for uh service oriented
architecture. So, um so what's from your
point of view? You already said that's
basically an architectural metaphor or a
blueprint. So, what are the most
important characteristics of an SOA from
your point of view?
So, basically the first important thing
is that everything is really using
explicit interfaces. So, in contrast to
CORBA for instance or COM, we're really
directly addressing a component, you
only see interfaces. So, you don't make
yourself dependent on implementations.
And that's basically the first thing.
Explicit interfaces are really important
here. I think the second thing is uh
that for instance everything is really
loosely coupled. Uh there's a good book
around which is called loose coupling by
the K, I guess. And that's a very
interesting book because it really deals
with all of these loose coupling things
like late binding and
using registries in order to find the
services. Don't think that there are
fixed connections between the client and
the service. So, basically all of these
things are really important in this
area. So, it's basically interfaces and
of course also the contracts. Every
interface is defined by a contract, is
expressed by a contract which basically
tells you what is the service really
providing to you in terms of the
services and where is it really located?
And I think in the future there will be
additional things in the contract like
semantic things. For instance, what
exactly is the ontology of the services
provided by your service interface or
what kind of quality of service will be
provided? I guess that's something which
will happen in the future.
Yeah, people talk about service level
agreements there and
one of my current customers which I
probably shouldn't name here
also currently works on establishing an
SOA and and it's really funny because
I've worked a lot in the component-based
development area and I can use all my
meta models that I used for
component-based development. I can reuse
them in SOA. Where do you see the
connection between component-based
development where you also have
explicitly defined interfaces where you
explicitly deploy things where you
configure components? Where do you see
the relationship between CBD and SOA?
From my viewpoint, component-based
development is more focusing on
remoting. Basically, if you look at the
component middleware
applications which you will see now,
most of them are really
basing on remoting middleware. So,
calling a method the method
in this case is executed in a component
and so on. All of these things are more
remoting-oriented and I think service
orientation, SOAP especially, is more on
the messaging paradigm. So, you're
sending a message to an object. So,
basically, it's more the old style of
object orientation which came in by
Smalltalk for instance.
So, I think that's one of the big
differences between regular
component-based development and service
orientation. But, of course,
this also depends on what kind of
definition you have in your speaking
about component-based development.
The point from my point of view in
component-based development is that you
have clearly defined building blocks
which define what they provide and what
which also define which interface they
require. So, you can do some decent
dependency management.
Sure.
Yeah.
Sorry, only one point which I forgot
is that service orientation is nothing
else than a continuous evolution of
object orientation and component based
development. So, I think it's comes to
no surprise that service orientation is
really an addition or an extension of
component based development.
Right. That Right, that's what I think
too. And it's basically lessons learned
from component based development where
things were sometimes too tightly
coupled and stuff. So, now you do some
more, you know, like more messaging
style or document centric
instead of having these tightly coupled
interfaces.
But, you know, if if you talk with
managers, you you hear all this business
driven and process integrated and policy
based
I really I mean, it's really hard to to
not lose your temper.
Yeah, it's it's a new hype. And that's
basically the danger because people
start to think of the hype as as it
would be a real working technology which
would solve all of your problems. And
that's basically not the case.
Right. Another thing that I I'd briefly
like to visit is
um
You talked about uh your research
projects at Siemens and you mentioned
aspect oriented and model driven
development. Do you see uh a specific
relationship between aspect orientation
and middleware in general or between
model driven development and SOA? So,
any any any synergies that are
particularly interesting?
Sure. Because as I said before, I'm
coordinating a research program which is
dealing with platform and product line
development and for distributed systems.
And we have all of these projects in
there. For instance, the AOSD project
and the model driven project and the
service orientation project. And all of
them are trying to find what are the
synergies. And for instance, one of the
synergies that we came up with was in
the model driven area. For instance, if
you are dealing with domain specific
languages, for instance, then what you
get if you're using people as an example
in the service orientation, then if you
want to express things like workflows,
also that's basically a domain specific
language. And you can really use tools
in order to take that domain specific
language in order to generate something
like an service oriented application. So
I think there are some really
interesting
things which you can do using model
driven software development techniques
in order to build service oriented
architectures. And I think a similar
issue for aspect orientation, if you
look at let's say JBoss AOP and all of
these things interceptor based
frameworks for instance like spring. I
think the same thing will really happen
if you use service orientation. So we
have built internally an open source
framework for service orientation which
is called fast. So it's basically
something like a package which tries to
integrate things like web service tool
kits and XML based databases and so on.
And in order to make the life easier for
the for the operator, we have come up
with something which is called an
interceptor AOP framework so that the
operator is basically able to intercept
all incoming web service requests and do
something else with it using his own
kind of scripting language for instance.
So basically AOP might for instance be
helpful in service orientation to add
functionality for an operator or even
adds the same thing like what spring is
doing for instance or JBoss does AOP is
doing add some functionality out of the
band functionality into your processing
of the service oriented system.
So one could maybe say that
AO can be used to make the middleware
configurable to add as you said out of
band services or or functionality and
and model driven development maybe helps
to to keep control of the overall system
to describe components services so that
you can you know understand and and and
and track what's happening because you
don't lose the overview.
Yes, I think one of the examples, if you
speak about software service oriented
architecture, then basically most people
think about business processes. And if
you look at business processes, one
thing for instance, one, let's say
cross-cutting concerns are business
rules. For instance, if you have
business rules which are impacting
different areas of the applications,
then basically a business rule engine, I
would also consider as a kind of
aspect-oriented uh
approach for So, basically, aspect
orientation would also be helpful in
order to do something like integrating
business rules, all of these things. So,
basically, that's what I think would be
an appropriate relationship and
synergy between service orientation and
aspect orientation.
Mhm. So, that you would basically say
you have You define the business rules
once and then you use AO-like approaches
to make sure they're enforced on the
server and maybe even on the client some
kind of validations and maybe also maybe
in the middleware to enforce some
quality of service things.
Sure. And I think the nice thing would
be because service orientation tries to
be implementation agnostic. So, if you
would come up with, let's say, method
interceptor interfaces that would be
independent of, let's say, .NET or Java
2 EE or whatever technology you're
using, then you could even build
interceptors or aspects independently
technology in which you are using these
aspects. So, basically, you could really
decouple the aspects and their
implementation from the actual
implementation of this rest of the
system, for instance.
Mhm. Mhm.
Um since you mentioned J2EE and .NET, a
couple of years ago, I I think I I once
stood in for you and did at a talk that
compared um
.NET and J2EE. I think that was on the
ACCU conference in 2002 maybe. So, um
looking back, what what's your
perspective perspective now? How have
the two platforms developed? Uh where do
you think which of the two platforms is
better suited for particular things?
Like for example, using J2EE J2EE for
enterprise system and .NET for clients.
Do you have any opinion there? Can you
compare the two platforms briefly and
say where they have their strengths?
I think it's a really difficult to
compare them because there are so many
things around and basically there's so
many layers because if you compare .NET
with Java, you can compare different
things like comparing the virtual
machines, comparing the libraries,
comparing the IDEs. But basically from
my viewpoint, if you only look at the
middleware stuff,
then I think there a lot of different
things happening there. For instance, in
the .NET world, if you look at the
Windows Communication Foundation, you
have something which I would call an
enterprise service bus. It's basically
Can you briefly explain what WCF stand
what what what it is?
So, it's the Windows Communication
Foundation, originally named Indigo, and
it's basically something which extends
.NET remoting. It's an integration of
.NET remoting, MSMQ, web services, and
basically it provides something like an
container-based framework where you can
really get SOAP-based messages, but
independent of the underlying transport
protocol, where you can consume these
messages and on a kind of remoting-based
paradigm send messages around, invoke
other services on other nodes, and use
different kinds of cross-cutting
concerns like security, which are
already in the container. So, basically,
it's a really highly configurable open
implementation, something which I really
could would call an enterprise service
bus implementation where everything can
be exchanged, everything is
configurable. You can add your own
protocol, so it's really something which
strongly
resembles .NET remoting, but it's a much
more flexible and configurable approach.
So, the the cynic in me would say it's
like EJB with web with with web services
on top.
Not really, because I think there are
differences between
Windows Communication Foundation EJB.
EJB basically is more a component-based
framework where with different kinds of
components, session components, uh
entity components. So, basically, the
Windows Communication Foundation
framework is not uh
caring about persistence, for instance,
which is basically a very important
thing uh at least from my viewpoint in
the EJB stuff.
So, basically, I think there are a lot
of differences, and I think the EJB uh
component containers are more used in
order to build enterprise-based
transaction-oriented systems, while the
Windows Communication Foundation is more
like CORBA. It's more
remoting service-based communication
platform and not a full-blown container
framework.
Okay, so you say .NET is hard to compare
with J2EE because it's because it's so
it has many different layers, but you
say that WCF is something that's that's
interesting. That's probably going to be
important.
Is that what you're saying among other
things?
You you can compare them, but because
basically you can build enterprise
systems either using Java 2 EE or
Microsoft.NET, but I see currently more
people using Java 2 EE for building
enterprise systems than they would use
.NET, for instance. So, basically,
that might change, and I think that will
change, but currently Java 2 EE seems to
be more suitable for building enterprise
systems that than .NET. That's basically
the reason why Microsoft is coming up
with these new WCF uh, framework.
Right. That was my impression too. When
when .NET was new, I remember being at
probably the OOP conference in Munich
and there was this
uh, case study talk by one of the German
insurance companies showing their
.NET project. But,
I mean, I'm more of a Java guy, but I
didn't see many really big enterprise
projects adopting .NET. There is really
more stuff going on in the J2EE world.
Absolutely. But, as I said before, that
might definitely change because I think
Java 2 E and Java especially have a very
long uh,
advantage because they were they're
really old now. Old in the positive
sense. So, basically they are mature
technologies and I think .NET is
something which is rapidly rapidly
developing, moving forward, and
also has some strengths which I see more
in the on the .NET side than on the Java
side, for instance. So, basically it's
better integrated, it's better using XML
stuff, for instance. It's a much better
implementation of web services. So, if
you look at Java, you get a lot of
toolkits with lot of different APIs. So,
basically it's more uniform. So, I think
there are a lot of advantages using
.NET, but uh, for the enterprise system
world, I really consider EGB, Spring,
and all of these things as much better
and much more advanced and much more
mature now.
Have you looked at uh, SCA, the service
component architecture?
A little bit. I had contact with a IBM
fellow, this Don Ferguson, and he was
here and visited us at Siemens and
showed us something about the SCA. So,
it's a really interesting approach and I
think that's something which is
definitely worth waiting for and
something which should have a big
influence in the future.
Right, but that's my impression too. And
also it it it looks
not not completely similar, but but
somewhat alike uh, Windows Communication
Foundation. It also has this this view
of a system. It has a more
message-oriented metaphor. So, it's
maybe better to compare WSC WCF with SCA
than comparing J2EE with .NET or
something.
If you look at the IBM WebSphere product
family, for instance, and if you look at
the development of WebSphere, I think
that basically WebSphere and SCA, for
instance, and in
WCF, the Windows Communication
Foundation, are
moving exactly in the same direction.
So, basically, I see
I would call them integrative middleware
solutions where you don't have to plug
in all of the different units from
yourself. You have to integrate
everything yourself, but where you get
really big support in building
components, integrating them independent
of the transport protocol used, or the
different kinds of services you need.
So, basically, they are really giving
you
big much advanced
handling of all of these distribution
development stuff.
I like to to get to to another topic. We
talked You mentioned before that
obviously you are one of the co-authors
of POSA one and two. So, you're quite
involved with patterns. So, how do you
think the the patterns community today,
how did you see the influence of your
especially of the POSA one patterns? I
think they're quite fundamental, the
architectural patterns in there. POSA
two is quite specialized for for some
people interesting, but it's not that
broad, I think. So, so, how do you see
the adoption of patterns in software
architecture?
When I'm in any of the Siemens projects,
then I think in compared to five, six
years ago when the first books came out,
for instance, then people are really
thinking with patterns. So, I don't have
to explain to developers anymore what a
pattern is, and that a pattern might be
valuable. I don't have to explain the
thing to managers. So, I think
at least in the projects where I am
involved, patterns are used, and there
is no resistance, and people really
think that's something which we should
use. It's probably like like like some
or or God, Michael Stahle is coming.
Let's quickly read the book and learn
all those pattern names.
Absolutely not.
It's not shocking. Five or six years
ago, I remember I was with Erich Gamma
at a conference and one of the
attendees
asked a question to Erich and asked him,
"I yes, I have built an application and
I've used all of your GoF patterns." And
Erich was really puzzled and it didn't
was really enjoying that kind of
question. And so basically, that's not
something which is really happening now.
So basically, people think that or see
that patterns are a very important tool.
It's one of many tools. You also have to
use UML or
modeling stuff and all of these things,
but patterns are really useful tool in
order to really fastly get the expertise
of other people into your system without
steadily reinventing the wheel. So
basically, something which really works.
And I think if you look at how many
people are using the Gang of Four
patterns for instance, and even the PoSA
patterns, I think are very widespread
now. I think people really think about
the patterns and really believe that
patterns are the real thing. They're
good thing to do and I don't think that
there are many people around currently
that don't consider patterns as a
valuable tool.
Yeah, I would also say patterns are part
of the mainstream now. And and one sign
that that shows that is that books with
a title blah blah blah blah patterns
don't sell anymore as good as they did
once. Maybe PoSA books, I don't know,
it's probably different. They probably
still sell 50,000 a year, but
um in general, the term pattern is not
something that's hyped anymore, which is
good because now it's part of the
mainstream.
Well, now you have the books with the
SOA in the title.
Right.
Okay.
So let's maybe let's wait until it's
mainstream.
I think the only thing which is
important about patterns, I think there
are not many people know that there are
several pattern conferences, the PLoP,
EuroPLoP, and other conferences.
And
about that in our early episode, but
it's again worth repeating, obviously.
And another thing which I think which is
really astonishing to me that people are
trying to that there
that there are not many things happening
in the community in terms of new books
coming out. I would have expected more
books on fundamental patterns like the
POSA one or GoF patterns, for instance.
And I'm really surprised that nothing in
this area is happening, basically. So,
Yeah, there are a lot of domain-specific
patterns like security patterns,
model-driven stuff, or or domain-driven
patterns, and
this
so are patterns already, Ajax patterns.
So, I think the the the literature form
of patterns is still used, but the
fundamental stuff, yeah, you're right,
there's not too much going on there.
when this pattern community started,
there was much more expectations here.
So, people really thought that after 5
10 years,
every there would be really big
encyclopedias with full of patterns,
everyone would know all of these
patterns, there would not only be
over 20 GoF patterns, but there would be
a really lot of different patterns which
you could use different kinds of search
strategies in order to find the right
patterns for your projects, and all of
these things didn't happen. But, on the
other side, um I think the the hype is
over, and people are really using
patterns and don't complaining about
using patterns, they're really in their
concrete projects using them, and that's
the good sign.
Yeah. Actually, isn't isn't Grady Booch
working on this this really really
really big architecture thingy which
also collects all existing patterns? I
think he has already collected like 200
or something. Do you know more details
about that?
more details. I only saw some messages
on his
webpage and where he spoke about his
book project and that's the only source
of information I have, but I I hope it
will really come out and not like the
Donald Knuth volume four.
Yeah, I think we have to get Grady Booch
on the show so he can talk about it.
Maybe let's try to get him.
That would be definitely an interesting
interview.
Okay, so one last thing I'd like to to
ask you is is
talking about software reuse
specifically since you mentioned your
involvement in software product product
lines before.
Many new paradigms have been invented in
order to facilitate reuse. Object
orientation, component based
development, and and probably SOA is
probably also about reusing services
over the enterprise. So, do you think
reusing software building blocks works
well or do you think that reusing
knowledge for example as in the form of
patterns works better? What do you think
what is working better in practice?
My personal opinion is that reusing
knowledge is much more pragmatic.
I can remember a few years ago when all
of these component type was around then
people started to build all of these
reuse repositories. And a former
colleague of mine asked me, "Oh, you're
building a repository, but you don't
have any reusable components. Does it
really make sense?" Basically, the
problem is for instance if you look at
the enterprise world or at specific
domains, then there will be no market in
building up components or services for a
very limited number of users. So,
basically think that does not work
definitely. What really works is reusing
expertise from other people because
basically experienced developers and
architects who are involved in different
projects can collect a big number of
different knowledge of expertise and
this could be made reusable using
patterns and think that's something
which is really working because it's not
something which you must use as it is as
it would be in an in a case of a
component. You can just use an idea and
the idea can be adapted to your own
needs. So you don't have to either use
the component or use nothing. So it's
more if you're using a pattern you can
adapt it to your own needs and that's
much more pragmatic from my viewpoint.
So basically my experience in all of the
projects I ever were there was the only
component which was
all the time we used which was called
grid.
So it was basically this grid grid which
you could use in all of these Microsoft
projects but all of the other components
were really difficult and I was in a big
project where different business units
had to agree what a patient for instance
is or what a customer is and that even
that did not work. So basically I'm not
I don't believe in all of these
reusability of component stuff.
That's really interesting because if you
look at the SOA discussions it's the
same thing again. You have this one
service that that you know provides
patient data. But again people have to
agree enterprise wide now
on what patient is or what the patient
data is.
Absolutely.
So running in the same problem again.
If you have a standardized kind of
service interface where everyone has to
abide to then this would definitely work
but I don't think this is something
which really works for all of all kinds
of problems and exactly if you look at
what people are using web services for
now is there any service in the UDDI
registries which a lot of people
UDDI?
No one uses UDDI and basically the idea
of UDDI was not only to discover
services but also to have a repository
of the reusable services everyone could
use. And I think there are legal
problems. The services don't fit the
external service standardization. So,
that can't possibly work. I don't
believe in this.
One problem we have at this customer I'm
working with currently
is that there is this one department
that when it asks for the data about a
customer, it wants all the data that
describes the customer and it it is it
is acceptable to wait like a second or
something. The other department, if they
ask for a customer, they only need basic
data, but they need it quickly because
they're in the call center. So, they
can't even agree on I mean, even if they
could agree on what data is used to
describe a customer, they couldn't agree
which percentage of it should be
returned when the service is asked for
the data. So, you have to describe
variants of services, you know, like
this one only returns a little bit of
the patient data. The other one returns
all the stuff and that becomes really
complex.
Yeah, and that's only two or three
stakeholders involved and think of about
hundreds or even thousands of
stakeholders which have to agree on all
of these things and that does not work.
Okay, so that that's good. So, we did
some SOA bashing. I think at some point
we need somebody on
on the show who who has a more positive
view on this topic and or yeah, so so he
can maybe defend SOA.
So, anything else you want to say before
we
finish this this episode?
Only last word. I'm not really
I'm not a
I really like service orientation, but
as I said before, I don't like web
services uh
as a tool which is really applicable for
everything. I think web services are
very strong in integrating different
middleware solutions on an enterprise
level and I think service orientation is
an architecture paradigm with things
like explicit interfaces, loose
coupling, contracts and all of these
things which is really valuable and you
can use it with CORBA or messaging
middleware. So, basically, don't try to
to combine both things into one one
pots. It's not only it's it's two
different things. It's service
orientation on one side, and on the
other side, it's web services. And both
have really strengths and weaknesses.
And and to add to that, um I I think
because I was bashing on SOA a little
bit, and I I didn't I didn't want to say
that SOA is bad, either. But the point
is that many of the problems that we had
in in in all these other paradigms,
which is agreeing on interfaces,
agreeing on data structures, dependency
management, all that stuff, it's still a
problem with SOA. It doesn't go away.
And people tend to forget that.
Absolutely. So, basically, the problems
remain the same, but the technology
techno- technologies and paradigms
change.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Okay. So, then, thanks for being on the
show.
Thank you very much.
This was another episode of Software
Engineering Radio.
The Software Engineering Radio team
wants to thank Henning Pauli for
providing the music, as well as
slipsen.com for hosting and bandwidth.
For more information on the podcast,
past episodes, and feedback, go to
se-radio.net.